A Register of the Vladislav Al'bionovich (Vl.)Maevskii Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Vladislav Al'bionovich (Vl.) Maevskii Papers
1869-1978
2009C10
Hoover Institution Archives
41 microfilm reels (6.15 linear feet)
These papers reflect the writings and research interests of Vladislav Al'bionovich Maevskii, church historian and theologian. Among his writings are works relating to late 19th and early 20th century history of the Eastern Orthodox Church, especially relating to Russian Orthodoxy, Mount Athos, and the Orthodox Church in the United States.
Maevskii, Vladislav Al'bionovich
Access
The collection is open for research
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2008
Alternative Forms of Material Available
A portion of the collection is available on Microfilm
Location of Original Materials
Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, Jordanville, New York
Chronology
1893 April 4 Born, Kremenchug, Russia
1913 Author, Putevye nabroski
1919 Staff Captain, White Army
1920 Evacuated from Odessa
1931 Graduated, Theological Faculty, Belgrade University
19?? Librarian, Patriarchal library, Belgrade
19?? Secretary to Patriarch Varnava (Rosich), Belgrade
1932 Author, Serbskii patriarkh Varnava i ego vremia
1934 Author, Revoliutsioner-monarkhist (Tikhomirov)
1936 Author, Narodyi patriarkh
1937 Author, Sviataia gora-Sremskie Karlovtsy
1940 Author, Neugasimyi svetil'nik
1941 Author, Lavra Khilendar
1945 Arrived in the U.S.A.
194?-19?? Professor, Saint Tikhon's Orthodox Theological Seminary, South Canaan, PA
1950 Author, Afonskie razskazy
1959 Author, Khristianstvo i sotsializm
1966 Author, Russkie v Iugoslavii
1969 Author, Afon i ego sud'ba
1973 Author, Istoricheskie ocherki
1975 January 16 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
These papers reflect the writings and research interests of Vladislav Al'bionovich Maevskii, church historian and theologian. Among his writings are works relating to late 19th and early 20th century history of the Eastern Orthodox Church, especially relating to Russian Orthodoxy, Mount Athos, and the Orthodox Church in the United States.
In emigration, Maevskii attended Belgrade University's theological faculty, and served as secretary to Patriarch Varnava (Rosich), and librarian of the Patriarchal library. As a result, Maevskii's scholarly activities included numerous topics relating to the Serbian Orthodox Church.
After arriving in the United States, Vladislav Maevskii became a member of the faculty of St. Tikhon's Orthodox Theological Seminary in South Canaan, PA. This appointment allowed Maevskii to focus on the history as well as contemporary issues of the Orthodox Church in the United States.
The correspondence file represents Maevskii's close contact with ecclesiastical figures, academicians, scholars, and representatives of the Russian émigré intelligentsia.
Maevskii's speeches and writings focus largely on his major research interests, and include drafts, notes, and typescripts of both published and unpublished works. Aside from topics relating to Church history, included are works on Rasputin, Russian and Serbian relations, and general topics relating to Russian history and Orthodox theology.
The Subject File includes materials on the history of the Russian Orthodox Church and especially on the various jurisdictional conflicts that affected the Church in emigration. Particularly important are documents dealing with conflicts of the Orthodox Church in the United States, reflected in collected correspondence of Church hierarchs of the Russian Orthodox Greek Catholic Church of America, the Russian Orthodox Church Outside Russia, conciliar minutes, epistles, and other related documents. Of special significance is Maevskii's research on the Athonite monks and monasteries.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Holy Trinity Seminary. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Holy Trinity Seminary Archives as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is appended to this register. Any views, findings, conclusions or recommendations expressed in these materials do not necessarily represent those of the National Endowment for the Humanities.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into eight series – Biographical file, Diary, Correspondence, Speeches and writings, Subject file, Photographs, Oversize file, Printed matter
Related Material
Archbishop Apollinarii (Koshevoi) Papers, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary
Archimandrite Amvrosii (Konovalov) Papers, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary
Konstantin Nikolaevich Nikolaev Papers, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary
Aleksandr Kallinikovich Svitich Papers, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary
Nikolai Dmitrievich Talberg Papers, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary
Separated Material
Most books and monographs have been separated to the library. See library catalog
Biography
Born on April 4, 1893, Vladislav Al’bionovich Maevskii began his literary career early, publishing his first work, a travelogue, in 1913, after enlisting as volunteer in the Balkan War of 1912-1913. During the Civil War, he joined the White Army as staff captain in 1919, evacuating to Constantinople from the Crimea in 1920 and then immigrating to Serbia, where he enrolled in the Theology Department of Belgrade University, graduating in 1931. Maevskii was a close friend of Patriarch Varnava (Rusich), serving both as his secretary and as librarian of the patriarchal library. In Serbia, Maevskii, who regularly contributed to Russian émigré periodicals, published several monographs on Russian and Serbian church history, Russian history and Mount Athos, which he visited several times and which occupied an important place in his writings.
In 1945, Maevskii immigrated to the United States, having been invited to teach at St. Tikhon’s Orthodox Theological Seminary in South Canaan, Pennsylvania. During his time at St. Tikhon’s, Maevskii invited Bishop Nikolaj (Velimirovic), subsequently canonized by the Serbian Orthodox Church, to join the seminary’s faculty. Maevskii taught a wide variety of subjects, both theological and historical, and continued to publish not only books but also articles in the Russian émigré press until his death.
Vladislav A. Maevskii died on January 16, 1975, in New Yor
Orthodox Eastern Church--United States.; Russian Orthodox Greek Catholic Church of America.; Serbian Orthodox Church.; Arkhiepiskopiia pravoslavnykh russkikh tserkvei v zapadnoi Evrope.; Athos (Greece); Diaries.; Photographs.; Russia--History.; Russians--Foreign countries.; Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov' zagranitsei.; Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov'.; Soviet Union.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Biographical file, 1931-1967 and undated. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes address book, diploma, clippings, identification documents, and immigration documents. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Address book, undated (Folder 1: 1)
  - Diploma, 1931. (Folder 1: 2)
    Issued in Belgrade, Yugoslavia
  - Family file, 1957-1967 and undated. (Folder 1: 3)
    Clippings of articles by Elena Maevskaia (wife), and mathematics exercises of Marina Maevskii (daughter)
  - Identification documents, 1936-1947 and undated. (Folder 1: 4)
    Includes name tags and travel documents
  - Immigration documents, 1947-1949. (Folder 1: 5)
    Includes related correspondence
- Diary, 1911-1912 (Folder 1: 6)
- Correspondence, 1928-1973 and undated.
  Cards and letters, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General – Drafts, 1928 and undated (Folder 1: 7)
  - Unidentified, 1936-1969 and undated (Folder 1: 8)
  - Afanasii (Shelepov), Abbott, 1956-1969 and undated (Folder 1: 9)
  - Almazova, M., 1957 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Anastasii (Gribanovskii), Metropolitan, 1951-1963 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Arsenii (Mikhalevskii), Abbott, undated. (Folder 1: 12)
    Includes two prints
  - Athenagoras, Patriarch, 1952 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Bezsmertnyi, Aleksandr E., 1950-1971 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Bobrov, V. N., 1957 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Bok, Mariia Petrovna, 1960-1962 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Bozhadzhevich, Il'ia, 1950 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Borisevich, Boris, Reverend, 1952 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Brasol (Brazol'), Aleksandr, 1969. (Folder 2: 3)
    Includes letter from Dmitrii Pavlov to A. Brasol
  - Buben, Mikhail, Reverend, 1952 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Chazov, Sergei S., 1962-1964 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Chepeleff, John, Reverend, 1959-1969 and undated. (Folder 2: 6)
    Includes three pamphlets and related correspondence
  - Czap, Ivan Michaelson, 1957-1968 and undated. (Folder 2: 7)
    Includes The Holy Mount Athos and the Slavs
  - Devrnja, Milutin, 1952-1966 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Deitrikh, Vsevolod, 1960 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Delfa, Ivan Ivanovich, 1950 (Folder 2: 10)
  - Delianich, A., 1973 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Dem'ianov, Mikhail, 1958. (Folder 2: 12)
    Includes one print
  - Demidov, Vasilii, Reverend, 1951 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Denikina, Kseniia V., 1952-1954 and undated (Folder 2: 14)
  - Dimitrii (Magan), Archbishop, 1956-1959 (Folder 2: 15)
  - D'iachenko, Antonii, Reverend, 1957 (Folder 2: 16)
  - Dirga, Michael, Reverend, 1964 (Folder 2: 17)
  - Feodora (L'vova), Abbess, 1960-1967. (Folder 2: 18)
    Includes six prints of the Holy Virgin Convent in Provement, France
  - Fedorenko, Ioann, Reverend, 1956 (Folder 2: 19)
  - Fedorov, Nikolai Ivanovich, 1955-1965 (Folder 2: 20)
  - Gerasim (Shmal'ts), Archimandrite, 1956 (Folder 2: 21)
  - German (Doric), Patriarch, 1968-1971 (Folder 2: 22)
  - Glibonijska, Danitsa, 1951 (Folder 2: 23)
  - Grebenshchikov, Georgii, 1948-1956 and undated (Folder 2: 24)
  - Horvath, Artemii A., 1969 (Folder 2: 25)
  - Il'in, Ivan Aleksandrovich, 1954 (Folder 2: 26)
  - Ioann (Shakhovskoi), Archbishop, 1956-1970 (Folder 2: 27)
  - Iovan (?), Archimandrite, 1956 (Folder 2: 28)
  - Irinei (Bekish), Archbishop, 1962-1963 (Folder 2: 29)
  - Jula, Stephen, Reverend, 1956-1959 (Folder 2: 30)
  - Kamenskii, Vasilii M., 1954-1969 (Folder 2: 31)
  - Kartashev, Anton Vladimirovich, 1954-1961 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Kasperskii, Leonid, Reverend, 1957-1968 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Khmelevskii, Aleksandr Dmitrievich, 1968 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Kiprian (Borisevich), Bishop, 1961-1962 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Kiranova, Vera, 1955 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Kohanik, Peter, Reverend, 1959 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Koriakov, Aleksei, 1968 (Folder 3: 7)
  - Kostich, L. M., 1959 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Kotova, O., 1951-1953 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Kovalevskii, Petr E., 1954 (Folder 3: 10)
  - Kusko, Andrei, 1968 (Folder 3: 11)
  - Kutyrina, Iu. A., 1954-1955 (Folder 3: 12)
  - Leontii (Filippovich), Archbishop, 1963-1969 (Folder 3: 13)
  - Leontii (Turkevich), Metropolitan, 1950-1962 (Folder 3: 14)
  - Levine, Isaac Don, 1956. (Folder 3: 15)
    Includes clipping
  - Likhodei, Pavel Andreevich, 1964-1966 (Folder 3: 16)
  - Maklakov, Vasilii Alekseevich, 1954-1957 and undated (Folder 3: 17)
  - Mal'chevskii, Aleksei Pavlovich, 1969 (Folder 3: 18)
  - Mel'nikov, N. A., 1964 (Folder 3: 19)
  - Mesniaev, Grigorii Valer'ianovich, 1968-1969 (Folder 3: 20)
  - Mladenovich, M., Reverend, 1970 (Folder 3: 21)
  - Mosconas, Theodor, 1952 (Folder 3: 22)
  - Nadezhda (?), Abbess, 1970 and undated (Folder 3: 23)
  - Nadezhdin, Mikhail Iosifovich, 1960 and undated (Folder 3: 24)
  - Navrotskii, Iurii Aleksandrovich, 1957-19 (Folder 3: 25)
  - Nekliudov, N. M., 1961-1962 (Folder 3: 26)
  - Nekliudova, Elizaveta Anatol'evna, 1957-1960 (Folder 3: 27)
  - Nikodim (?), Monk, 1961-1966 (Folder 3: 28)
  - Nikolaev, Konstantin Nikolaevich, 1959-1961 (Folder 3: 29)
  - Nikolai (Efremov), Monk, 1954 (Folder 3: 30)
  - Nikolai (Velimirovich), Bishop, 1951-1952 (Folder 3: 31)
  - Nikon (Greve, de), Archbishop, 1956-1970 and undated (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Nikon (Rklitskii), Archbishop, 1960-1970 (Folder 4: 2)
  - Nikitin, Dimitrii Vladimirovich, 1956-1961 and undated. (Folder 4: 3)
    Includes two prints, a short memoir and an article on St. John of Kronstadt
  - Novikov, V. K., 1947-1962 and undated (Folder 4: 4)
  - Novitskii, Evgenii, 1962-1966 (Folder 4: 5)
  - Obrazkova, Ianina, 1970 (Folder 4: 6)
  - Onore, Nicholas, 1969-1970 and undated (Folder 4: 7)
  - Oznobishin, D., 1949-1952 (Folder 4: 8)
  - Pavlov, Dimitrii, 1969-1970 (Folder 4: 9)
  - Platonov, S., 1969-1971 (Folder 4: 10)
  - Pol'skii, Mikhail, Reverend, 1958 (Folder 4: 11)
  - Prokopovich, Ekaterina, 1949-1954 (Folder 4: 12)
  - Pronin, Vasilii Mikhailovich, 1958-1960 and undated. (Folder 4: 13)
    Includes several articles by Pronin and clipping
  - Pushkarev, Sergei Germanovich, 1964-1971 and undated. (Folder 4: 14)
    Includes printed copy of Pushkarev's article "Vneshniaia politika Lenina," signed by author, and related clippings
  - Red'kin, Aleksandr P., 1963-1965 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Riabushinskii, D., 1954 (Folder 5: 2)
  - Riabushinskii, V., 1954 (Folder 5: 3)
  - Rostkovskaia, Mariia, 1960-1961. (Folder 5: 4)
    General note
    See also Correspondence/Shumskaia, A.
  - Rubanov, Lev S., 1964-1967. (Folder 5: 5)
    Includes lists of Russian books published in Brazil
  - Rusanov, Fedor, 1965 (Folder 5: 6)
  - Russkii klich, 1967. (Folder 5: 7)
    Includes two articles on Archbishop Ioann (Shakhovskoi)
  - Semenov-Tian' Shanskii, Nikolai, 1961-1965 (Folder 5: 8)
  - Seminitsa, Nina, 1965 (Folder 5: 9)
  - Seniutovich, Viachaslav Georgievich, 1971 (Folder 5: 10)
  - Serafim (Ivanov), Archbishop, 1954 (Folder 5: 11)
  - Sergievskii, Boris N., 1964-1965 (Folder 5: 12)
  - Sharov, Nikolai, 1946 (Folder 5: 13)
  - Shavel'skii, Georgii, Reverend, 1949 (Folder 5: 14)
  - Shmelev, Ivan Sergeevich, 1948-1950 (Folder 5: 15)
  - Shtrandman, Vasilii Nikolaevich, 1957-1958. (Folder 5: 16)
    Includes clippings
  - Shumskaia, A., 1960. (Folder 5: 17)
    See also Correspondence/Rostkovskaia, Mariia
  - Shuberskii, A. N., 1960 (Folder 5: 18)
  - Sil'vestr (Kharuns), Archbishop, 1968 (Folder 5: 19)
  - Slepecky, Andrew, Reverend, 1963 (Folder 5: 20)
  - Sokolov, Boris, 1948 (Folder 5: 21)
  - Solntsev, K. I., 1956-1960 (Folder 5: 22)
  - St. Tikhon's Orthodox Theological Seminary, 1950-1960 and undated. (Folder 5: 23)
    Includes related notes
  - Stavrovskii, Aleksei, 1963-1968 (Folder 5: 24)
  - Struve, Gleb, 1962 (Folder 5: 25)
  - Svishchev, Ivan S., 1960-1968 (Folder 5: 26)
  - Svitich, Aleksandr Kallinikovich, 1961 (Folder 5: 27)
  - Svitich, Lidiia, 1959-1966. (Folder 5: 28)
    Includes correspondence of Aleksandr K. Svitich forwarded to Maevskii by Lidiia Svitich
  - Tikhomirov, Dimitrii M., 1969-1970 (Folder 5: 29)
  - Tikhon (Troitskii), Archbishop, 1952 (Folder 5: 30)
  - Timotheus, Patriarch of Jerusalem, 1952. (Folder 5: 31)
    Includes calendar of the Patriarchate of 1952
  - Tolstoy, Alexandra L., 1970-1971 (Folder 5: 32)
  - Tomashevskaia, Elizaveta, 1957 (Folder 5: 33)
  - Troitskii, Sergei, 1938-1962 (Folder 5: 34)
  - Trufanov, Sergei Mikhailovich, aka "Patriarch Iliodor,", 1947-1950. (Folder 5: 35)
    Includes Pamiatka o vechnoi istine
  - Vertsinskii, E. A., 1938 (Folder 5: 36)
  - Vissarion (?), Reverend, 1954 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Vladimir (?), Bishop, 1951 (Folder 6: 2)
  - Voloshin, Aleksandr, 1958-1960. (Folder 6: 3)
  - Zaitsev, Boris, 1954-1960 (Folder 6: 4)
  - Zalenskii, E., 1966 (Folder 6: 5)
  - Zemmering, Raissa, 1958 (Folder 6: 6)
  - Zernov, Nicholas, 1962-1969 (Folder 6: 7)
- Speeches and writings, 1912-1971 and undated.
  Articles, bibliographies, clippings, drafts, lectures, notes, pamphlets, and scrapbooks, arranged chronologically by title
  - General
    - Articles
      - Untitled, undated. (Folder 6: 8-10)
        Holograph and typescript
      - Untitled, undated. (Box-folder 7: 1-3)
      - Untitled, 1951. (Folder 7: 4)
        Typescript
      - Russian literature, undated. (Folder 7: 5)
        Holograph and typescript. Includes articles on various famous Russian writers
    - Bibliographies, undated (Folder 7: 6)
    - Lectures.
      Typescripts, includes handwritten notes and background materials
      - Canon law, 1951-1952 and undated. (Folder 7: 7)
      - Church history, 1952-1957 and undated (Box-folder 8: 1)
      - Comparative theology, undated (Folder 8: 2)
      - Dogmatic theology, 1950-1951 and undated (Folder 8: 3)
      - History of religion, 1955-1956 (Folder 8: 4)
      - History of the Russian Orthodox Church in America, 1950-1963 (Folder 8: 5)
      - Patrology, undated (Folder 8: 6)
      - Russian Church history, undated (Folder 8: 7)
    - Letters to the editor, undated (Folder 8: 8)
    - Notebooks, undated (Box 9)
      - General (Folder 9: 1)
      - "Germantsy" (Folder 9: 2)
      - "Khristianskoe iskusstvo" (Folder 9: 3)
      - "Kleveta na Boga" (Folder 9: 4)
      - "Love" (Folder 9: 5)
      - "Nishchie dukhom i gordye" (Folder 9: 6)
      - "Patriarshestvo na Rusi" (Folder 9: 7)
      - Russian history (Folder 9: 8)
      - Serbian Church history (Folder 9: 9)
      - Serbian-Russian relations (Folder 9: 10)
      - "Tsesarepapizm" (Folder 9: 11)
      - "Uchastlivyia otnosheniia Rossii k slavianam" (Folder 9: 12)
  - General
    - Notes, undated (Box-folder 10: 1-3)
    - Research notes, undated.
      Handwritten and typed notes, article drafts, includes limited amount of clippings
      - General (Folder 10: 4)
      - Athos (Folder 10: 5)
      - Canonization (Folder 10: 6)
      - Nativity of Christ (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - Reviews
      - General, 1934-1962 and undated. (Folder 11: 2)
        Typescript and clippings
      - "Bibliografiia i kritika,", 1954 and undated. (Folder 11: 3)
    - Scrapbooks, articles pasted by the author. (Folder 11: 4-6)
      See also Oversize file/Scrapbooks
    - Scrapbooks (Box 12-14)
    - Scrapbook (Box-folder 15: 1)
  - Untitled typescript on P. A. Stolypin, undated (Folder 15: 2)
  - Untitled typescript on the history of the Lesna convent, undated. (Folder 15: 3)
    Includes related correspondence, corrections, and memoirs
  - Untitled typescript on Russian church history, undated (Folder 15: 4)
  - "Adriaticheskaia ekspeditsiia,", undated. (Folder 15: 5)
  - "Afon,", undated. (Folder 15: 6)
    Typescript, includes related articles and notes
  - "Afonskaia smuta,", undated. (Folder 15: 7)
    Holograph, includes related clippings, drafts and notes
  - "Alyia zori,", undated. (Folder 15: 8)
  - "Anakhronizm velikogo Repina,", undated. (Folder 15: 9)
  - "Anglikanskoe verouchenie,", undated. (Folder 15: 10)
    Holograph, typescript. Includes related notes
  - "Arkhiereiskii konflikt,", undated. (Folder 15: 11)
    Holograph
  - "Arkhipelagom k Maloi Azii,", undated. (Folder 15: 12)
  - "Azem Beita,", undated. (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - "Bednaia Dasha,", undated. (Folder 16: 2)
  - "Beregite dukhovenstvo,", undated. (Folder 16: 3)
  - "Beregite veru,", undated. (Folder 16: 4)
  - "Bezbrachie dukhovenstva,", undated. (Folder 16: 5)
  - "Bezzakoniia vselenskogo patriarkhata,", undated. (Folder 16: 6)
    Typescript. Includes related materials
  - "Blagodat' Bozhiia,", undated. (Folder 16: 7)
  - "Blagodat' eretikov,", undated. (Folder 16: 8)
  - "'Bogoiskateli' iz intelligentsii,", undated. (Folder 16: 9)
    Typescript, includes related clipping and draft
  - "Bogootkrovennost' Biblii,", undated. (Folder 16: 10)
  - "Bozh'i pchely,", undated. (Folder 16: 11)
  - "Bukhta Kattaro,", undated. (Folder 16: 12)
    Typescript, includes related materials
  - "Bytopisatel' dukhovenstva,", undated. (Folder 16: 13)
    Typescript, includes related material
  - "Chem glubzhe skorb', tem blizhe Bog,", undated. (Folder 16: 14)
  - "Chistota very,", undated. (Folder 16: 15)
  - "Chtyi da razumeet,", undated. (Folder 16: 16)
  - "Dela davno minuvshikh dnei, predan'ia stariny glubokoi,", undated. (Folder 16: 17)
    Holograph, typescript
  - "Dela tserkovnye-obshchenarodnye,", undated. (Folder 16: 18)
  - "Den' vozneseniia Gospodnia,", undated. (Folder 16: 19)
    Typescript, includes related articles
  - "Denatsionalizatsiia russkoi emigratsii,", undated. (Folder 16: 20)
  - "Detstvo vo Khriste,", undated. (Folder 16: 21)
  - "Diakony,", undated. (Folder 16: 22)
  - "Diplomaticheskii avantiurizm,", undated. (Folder 16: 23)
  - "Dlia chego nuzhna religiia?", undated. (Folder 16: 24)
  - "Dlinnye vlasy i voskryliia,", undated. (Folder 16: 25)
  - "Dni drevnie i nashi dni,", undated. (Folder 16: 26)
  - "Doblestnye spodvizhniki velikogo Suvorova,", undated. (Folder 16: 27)
    Typescript, includes related clipping and notes
  - "Dobrodietel' i strasti,", undated. (Folder 16: 28)
  - "Dogmat i chastnoe bogoslovskoe mnenie,", undated. (Folder 16: 29)
  - "Dogmat i ego is"iasnenie,", undated. (Folder 16: 30)
  - "Dorevoliutsionnaia Rossiia i SSSR,", undated. (Folder 16: 31)
  - "Dostovernost' i podlinnost' evangelii,", undated. (Folder 16: 32)
  - "Drevnii mir,", undated. (Folder 16: 33)
  - "Drevnii mir i rabstvo,", undated. (Folder 16: 34)
  - "Drug Rossii i russkikh,", undated. (Box-folder 17: 1)
  - "Dukh ierarkhizma,", undated. (Folder 17: 2)
  - "Dukhovenstvo,", undated. (Folder 17: 3)
  - "Dukhovenstvo i prikhozhane,", undated. (Folder 17: 4)
  - "Dukhovnaia sila lichnosti,", undated. (Folder 17: 5)
  - "Dukhovnyi golod,", undated. (Folder 17: 6)
  - "Dukhovnyi oblik Vladyki Nikolaia,", undated. (Folder 17: 7)
  - "Dve glavnye opasnosti,", undated. (Folder 17: 8)
    Typescript. Includes related material
  - "Dve sdachi/peredachi korablei (russkikh anglichanam),", undated. (Folder 17: 9)
  - "Dzhek London,", undated. (Folder 17: 10)
  - "Edinenie khristianskikh tserkvei,", undated. (Folder 17: 11)
  - "Edinoglasie i edinodushie,", undated. (Folder 17: 12)
  - "Edinovlastie i sobornost',", undated. (Folder 17: 13)
  - "Ekumenicheskoe dvizhenie,", undated. (Folder 17: 14)
  - "Episkopskoe vystuplenie,", undated. (Folder 17: 15)
    Typescript, includes related notes
  - "Eshche o 'svobode' Tserkvi,", undated. (Folder 17: 16)
  - "Est'-li besy?", undated. (Folder 17: 17)
  - "Frantsuzy na russkoi sluzhbe,", undated. (Folder 17: 18)
  - "Gadaniia na Ukraine,", undated. (Folder 17: 19)
  - "Ganibal v Sibiri,", undated. (Folder 17: 20)
  - "Gde prichina pechal'nogo iavleniia?", undated. (Folder 17: 21)
  - "General graf K. M. Ivelich,", undated. (Folder 17: 22)
  - "General Skobelev,", undated. (Folder 17: 23)
  - "Geroi bezvremen'ia,", undated. (Folder 17: 24)
  - "Gosudarevy sapery,", undated. (Folder 17: 25)
  - "Gosudarstvennye prestupniki,", undated. (Folder 17: 26)
  - "Graf Simeon Zorich,", undated. (Folder 17: 27)
  - "Ibragim Gannibal i Savva Raguzinskii,", undated. (Folder 17: 28)
    Typescript. Includes related drafts and notes
  - "Ideal'noe poniatie Tserkvi,", undated. (Folder 17: 29)
  - "Ideia khristianskogo vossoedineniia,", undated. (Folder 17: 30)
  - "Ideia sobornosti,", undated. (Folder 17: 31)
  - "Iisus Khristos–Bogochelovek,", undated. (Folder 17: 32)
  - "Iisus Khristos kak lichnost',", undated. (Folder 17: 33)
    Typescript, includes related clippings
  - "Inostrantsy i inostrannoe vliianie v Rossii,", undated. (Folder 17: 34)
  - "Ioannity,", undated. (Folder 17: 35)
  - "Iskateli istiny,", undated. (Folder 17: 36)
  - "Istina Khristova i put' zhizni,", undated. (Folder 17: 37)
  - "Istoricheskaia spravka (kanonizatsiia russkikh sviatykh),", undated. (Folder 17: 38)
    Holograph, typescript, includes related notes
  - "Istoricheskaia spravka (s"ezdy eparkhial'nogo dukhovenstva),", undated. (Folder 17: 39)
  - "Istoricheskii podvig drevnei Rusi,", undated. (Folder 17: 40)
  - "Istoricheskoe khristianstvo i neokhristianstvo,", undated. (Folder 17: 41)
  - "Istoriia gosudarstva rossiiskogo,", undated. (Folder 17: 42)
  - "Istoriia i znachenie gazety,", undated. (Folder 17: 43)
  - "Istoriia russkoi zemli,", undated. (Folder 17: 44)